Guide to the Lighthouse Photograph and Print Collection [1860]-1938 PR 38
New-York Historical Society
Lighthouse Photograph and Print Collection
[1860]-1938
New-York Historical Society
PR 38
7.84 Linear feet (7 boxes and 1 oversize volume)
Collection of photographs and prints depicting lighthouses, light vessels, and related equipment, primarily in the United States, from about 1860 through 1938. A few views of foreign lighthouses and equipment are included, as is an album of lithographs of architectural plans, sections, and elevations for lighthouses, light vessels, lenses, and other equipment.
Provenance
The bulk of the Lighthouse Photograph and Print Collection was acquired through two gifts. Admiral Edward H. Smith donated 335 photographs on July 19, 1946, on behalf of the Third Division of the U.S. Coast Guard, New York City. On February 10, 1953, The Metropolitan Museum of Art Library donated a series of 35 albumen photographs taken by the Halliday Historic Photograph Co. of Boston documenting lighthouses located in Maine and Massachusetts. A third component of this collection is a bound volume containing 150 lithographs by Julius Bien produced for the U.S. Lighthouse Service; the provenance of this album is unknown, but it may at one time have belonged to Brigadier General Richard Delafield, Chief Engineer of the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers from 1864-1866.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to 30 photocopies per day per person. Suitability of the original for photocopying is at the discretion of the staff. Neither blueprints nor tracings can be copied under any circumstances. Duplication of large-format items will be done by the house photographer. See Print Room guidelines for details.
Historical Note
During the colonial period, American colonies each had individual financial and administrative control over their own lighthouses and other navigational aids. In 1716 the first American lighthouse began to guide sailors into Boston Harbor from its home on Little Brewster Island. By the time the colonies moved for independence from England in 1776, there were ten lighthouses in operation along the coastline. The newly-created Congress of the United States, meeting for its first session, recognized the important role maritime commerce played in the young nation's economy. In 1789, as its Ninth Act, the Congress provided for the federal takeover of all lighthouses and minor aids to navigation in its constituent states. This act also created the U.S. Light House Establishment and placed it under the administration of the Treasury Department. For the first few years many minor matters required review by Secretary of the Treasury Alexander Hamilton and signature by President George Washington. To simplify these processes, in 1792 the position of the Commissioner of Revenue was established to take over the leadership of the Light House Establishment. In the following years control would revert back and forth between these two administrators. Finally in 1820 superintendence was assumed by the Fifth Auditor of the Treasury Department, Stephen Pleasonton, who would hold the command for the following thirty years.
Pleasonton's administration was notoriously resistant to change, and visitors from Europe commented on the poor state of the navigational aids of the United States. Although the number of lighthouses and lightships grew to 325 by 1852, many were not considered reliable. Although French inventor Augustin Fresnel developed lenses capable of gathering and focusing a central light into a beam visible from far greater distances than traditional lights in 1823, the lenses were not used in the United States until 1841 when an imported Fresnel lens was installed in the Highlands of Navesink Light (New Jersey) marking the approach to New York Harbor.
Until technological advancement made the construction of offshore towers feasible, light vessels were strategically placed in waters considered inhospitable for lighthouses. The first lightship off the coast of the United States was installed near Sandy Hook in 1823.
In 1852, Congress dissolved the Light House Establishment and organized the new U.S. Light House Board. The Board organized the country into twelve districts, each administered by an inspector appointed by the President. The Light House Board oversaw great changes in navigational aids. It immediately began installing Fresnel lenses in its lighthouses and oversaw the building of new screwpile lighthouses, as well as new types of fog signals and buoys. Under its direction, the first lighthouses and fog signals went up on the Pacific Coast. In 1886 the Light House Board tested a new light source, electricity, to illuminate the torch of the Statue of Liberty in New York Harbor (which was then considered a key aid to navigation).
In 1910, the U.S. Light House Board was dissolved, and Congress established the Bureau of Lighthouses (better known as the Lighthouse Service). Finally in 1939, in the interest of efficiency, the Bureau of Lighthouses was integrated into the United States Coast Guard. The Coast Guard became responsible for the control and administration of approximately 30,000 navigational aids.
Scope and Content Note
The Lighthouse Photograph and Print Collection spans the period from about 1860 through 1938 and consists predominantly of photographs depicting American lighthouses, beacons, keepers' dwellings, lighthouse equipment, light vessels, and related subjects. The collection is arranged in five series: Cyanotype Album, Lighthouses, Floating Aids to Navigation, Light Station Equipment, and Lithograph Album by Julius Bien. Throughout this finding aid, names of lights have been standardized to those currently used by the U.S. Coast Guard and the U.S. National Park Service. Alternate or former names which are in popular usage are in parentheses after official names; names which could not be confirmed have been written in brackets.
The collection consists primarily of photographs of lighthouses and stations along the eastern coast of the United States, but lighthouses in California, Puerto Rico and England are also included. Light vessels, tenders (ships responsible for tending to buoys), and lighthouse equipment, including lights, lenses, audible signals, and engines are also included. Miscellaneous materials include views of exhibition displays, two pamphlets, a letter, and a few mounted clippings. The collection includes an album of cyanotype views of lighthouses and associated structures (ca. 1884-1900) and an album of lithographs by Julius Bien (ca. 1860).
Materials in this collection originate from a variety of photographers and publishers, and as a result, photographic styles vary. The collection includes both detailed technical work and commercially-produced scenic views. For the majority of materials in this collection, the photographer is unknown. Professional commissions include photography by Underhill, Alexander & Tolman, and the Fairchild Airviews Company, all of New York. Other large-scale surveys may have commissioned lesser known professional photographers or assigned staff photographers to systematically document U.S. Lighthouses. Photographer's names occasionally appear hand-written on the verso; names have been given in parentheses in the folder listing when available. There are a few survey series, including those of West Quoddy Head Light Station in Maine and Devil's Light Station in Wisconsin, which show stylistic consistency; they are all 8 x 10 inch contact prints with similar numeration and descriptive information set on the negatives and printed directly into the photographs. These may have been done by the same person, but it is more likely that they reflect Lighthouse Service standards for photographic documentation.
Arrangement
Missing Title
Series I: Cyanotype Album
Series II: Lighthouses
Series III: Floating Aids to Navigation
Series IV: Light Station Equipment
Series V: Lithograph Album by Julius Bien
Related Material at The New-York Historical Society
The John McComb Architectural Drawing Collection (PR 040) includes architectural drawings of Eaton's Neck Lighthouse (New York), Montauk Point Lighthouse (New York), and Cape Henry Lighthouse (Virginia).
Lighthouse tenders -- United States.; Lightships -- United States.; Beach erosion -- United States.; Cyanotypes; Albumen prints.; Lithographs.; Gelatin silver prints.; Building plans.; Sections; Elevations (orthographic projections).; Photographic prints.; Lighthouses -- United States.; Lighthouses -- Lighting; Bien, Julius, 1826-1909; United States. Lighthouse Service
- Series I: Cyanotype Album
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I dates from about 1884 to 1900 and includes undated cyanotypes from a disbound album compiled for the United States Light House Board. The photographs have been arranged alphabetically by state and thereunder by name. Most titles refer to lighthouses or stations, but a few photographs from the album depict fog bells, stake lights, or range lights; these exceptions are noted. An original album inventory is available in folder one, and corresponding index numbers have been noted in parentheses after each item. The album documents lighthouses throughout New England, New Jersey and New York, and includes images ranging in size from 5 x 7 inches to 13 ½ x 10 ½ inches. Folder 5 contains a comprehensive series of photographs documenting the Sandy Hook Light station, powerhouse, and bouy installation. Sixteen of the images printed as cyanotypes for this album are duplicated in Series II.
  - Original index to cyanotype album, [1900] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - Connecticut
    - Bridgeport Breakwater (Tongue Point) (11a), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    - Faulkner's Island (40) (2 items), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    - Housatonic River (52a), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    - Latimer Reef (59) (2 items), 1901 Jun. 20, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    - Morgan Point (66a), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    - New Haven Long Wharf (70), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    - New London Harbor (71) (3 items), [1884] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    - New London Steamer Putnam (141), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    - Penfield Reef (82), 1886 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - Maine
    - [Duck Island Breakwater, lost light] (32a)], 1899 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - New Jersey
    - Sandy Hook -- Electric Station Power House (interior) (104), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    - Sandy Hook -- Electric buoy - head, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    - Sandy Hook -- Electric buoy - in water, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    - Sandy Hook -- Electric junction box, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    - Sandy Hook -- Fog signal house, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    - Sandy Hook -- General view, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    - Sandy Hook -- Lower house, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    - Sandy Hook Light Vessel (16), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - New York
    - Coney Island (22) (3 items), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
    - Cumberland Head (34), 1900 Oct. 22 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
    - Danskammer Point Fog Bell (32), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
    - Eatons Neck (34), [1885] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - Elm Tree Range Light (35), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - Esopus Island (36), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - Execution Rocks (39) (2 items), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - Fort Columbus Fog Bell (48), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
    - Fort Lafayette Fog Bell (43), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
    - Fort Tompkins (44), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
    - Hell Gate Electric Light (52) (3 items), [1884-1886] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
    - Huntington Harbor (formerly Lloyd Harbor) (64) (2 items), 1885 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
    - Jeffrey's Hook (stake light)(56), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
    - Livingston Creek (beacon) (63), 1886 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
    - Montauk Point (66) (2 items), 1884 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
    - North Dumpling (75), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
    - Orient Point (79a), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
    - Plattsburgh (84), 1886 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
    - Plum Island (85), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
    - Port Jefferson (89a), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
    - Port Jefferson (elevated walk and fog house), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
    - Rockland Lake (96) (3 items), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
    - Rondout (98), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
    - Sands Point (103), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
    - Stony Point (16), 1886 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
  - Rhode Island
    - Block Island (North) (6), [1880] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
    - Brenton's Reef Light Vessel (Map) (10), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
    - Conimicut Shoal (23), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
    - Gould Island (47), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
    - Great Salt Pond Breakwater (50a) (2 items), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
    - Ida Lewis Rock (formerly Lime Rock), Ida Lewis pictured (61), 1884 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
    - Newport Harbor (Goat Island) (72) (2 items), 1884 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
    - Point Judith (87), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
    - Ponham Rocks (cyanotype fragments) (89) (4 items), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
    - Rose Island (99), [1884] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
    - Sabin's Point (Sabine Point) (100) (4 items), 1900 Nov. 14 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
  - Vermont
    - Juniper Island (58), 1886 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
  - Unidentified Locations
    - Otter Creek (80), 1900 Oct. 15 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
- Series II: Lighthouses
  Series II dates from about 1868 to 1938 and includes primarily undated mounted albumen and silver gelatin photographic prints of lighthouses, towers, and other components of light stations. Photographs are arranged in three subseries: American Lighthouses, Foreign and U.S. Territorial Lighthouses, and Unidentified Lighthouses. Thereunder photographs are arranged alphabetically by state (or country) and official name. Oversize materials have been filed in box 7. Folder 13 contains an alphabetical index (which probably was received with the collection) to fifty-two lighthouse photographs, only some of which are in this collection.
  Most American light stations represented are located along the eastern seaboard of the United States, between Maine and South Carolina. Among these are a group of about thirty mounted photographs of lighthouses located in Maine and Massachusetts which were taken by the Halliday Historic Photograph Co.; these photographs were a gift of the library of the Metropolitan Museum of Art. Halliday was a Boston firm which produced architectural and scenic views for commercial sale from the 1890s through the 1930s. Most of the Halliday photographs bear captions and plate numbers printed into the photographs; the verso of each has been labeled with "Halliday," the plate number, and a stamp from the Metropolitan Museum of Art. Other photographs represent lighthouses in California, Michigan, Minnesota, Florida, New Hampshire, Ohio, South Carolina, Vermont, and Wisconsin.
  The majority of the photographs in this series are general views of light stations or towers. Also included is a series of photographs documenting the United States Lighthouse Depot (now the National Lighthouse Museum) on Staten Island, New York. The U.S. Lighthouse Depot served as a national headquarters for the Lighthouse Board and as a center for testing new technologies, and building and repairing lighthouses, lightships and other equipment. Folders 31-32 include a group of beach erosion survey photographs taken in 1919 at Barnegat Light Station in New Jersey. A few photographs feature lighthouse keepers or other unidentified individuals; for example an 1884 photograph of the Ida Lewis Rock Lighthouse (formerly Lime Rock) in Rhode Island features Ida Lewis in front of the structure. (A duplicate cyanotype print of this image is available in Series I). The series also includes a set of identical clippings from a March 27, 1936, edition of the New York Daily News regarding a ship which ran aground near Race Rock Light, New York. Two pamphlets outlining a lighthouse cruise from Portland, Maine to New York are available with other oversize materials in Box 7.
  The subseries Foreign and U.S. Territorial Lighthouses consists of one photograph by Alfred Camm of Bishop's Rock Light in England, and a group of eighteen photographs of lighthouses in the U.S. Territory of Puerto Rico. Thirteen photographs of unidentified lighthouses are located in folder 51 at the end of this series.
  - American Lighthouses -- Index to Lighthouses, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
  - American Lighthouses -- California
    - Point Reyes (Punta de Los Reyes), [1870] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
  - American Lighthouses -- Connecticut
    - Black Rock Harbor, 1884 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
    - Bridgeport Harbor, 1884 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
    - Falkner's Island (Faulkner's Island) -- Building surveys (3 items), 1900 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
    - Falkner's Island (Faulkner's Island) -- General views (2 items), 1884 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
    - Lynde Point (Saybrook), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
    - Morgan Point, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
    - New Haven Outer Breakwall (Sperry Light) -- Foundation cylinder, 1899 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
    - New Haven Outer Breakwall (Sperry Light) -- Beacon and survey station, 1899 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
    - New London Harbor, 1884 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
    - Penfield Reef, 1886 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
    - Southwest Ledge, 1886 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
    - Stamford Harbor, 1886 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
    - Stonington Outer Breakwater, 1884 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
    - Stratford Point -- Original wooden tower (2 copies), [1870-1881] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
    - Stratford Point -- Cast iron tower (2 copies), 1884 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
  - American Lighthouses -- Florida
    - Amelia Island, [1880] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18)
    - Jupiter Inlet, [1880] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18)
    - St. Augustine, [1880] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18)
  - American Lighthouses -- Maine
    - Avery's Rock Machias Bay (2 items), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
    - Bass Harbor Head (2 items), [1880] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
    - Brown's Head, [1880] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
    - Burnt Island, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
    - Cape Elizabeth (east and west towers), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
    - Cape Neddick ("The Nubble") (4 items), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 20)
    - Dice Head (view from Nautilus Island), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 20)
    - Eagle Island, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 20)
    - Franklin Island, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 20)
    - Heron Neck, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 20)
    - Little River -- View from the water, [1892] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 21)
    - Little River -- General view (2 items), [1892] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 21)
    - Little River -- Fog bell, [1892] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 21)
    - Little River -- Boat house (2 items), [1892] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 21)
    - Little River -- Tower and dwelling, [1892] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 21)
    - Marshall Point, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 21)
    - Moose Peak Lighthouse, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 21)
    - Mount Desert Rock (3 items), [1890] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 22)
    - Nash Island (4 items), [1890] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 22)
    - Owls Head, [1890] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 22)
    - Petit Manan -- Boat house, [1892] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 23)
    - Petit Manan -- Light station (4 items), [1892] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 23)
    - Petit Manan -- Tower (2 items), [1892] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 23)
    - Portland Head, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 24)
    - Saddleback Ledge, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 24)
    - Seguin Island, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 24)
    - St. Croix River, [1890] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 24)
    - Tenants Harbor, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 24)
    - West Quoddy Head -- General views (6 items), 1892 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 25)
    - West Quoddy Head -- Powerhouse, 1892 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 25)
    - West Quoddy Head --Tower, 1892 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 25)
    - Whitehead Island, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 26)
    - Unidentified (4 items), undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 26)
  - American Lighthouses -- Massachusetts
    - Boston Harbor, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 27)
    - Eastern Point, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 27)
    - Marblehead, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 27)
    - Thatcher's Island (North) and Cape Ann (South), undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 27)
  - American Lighthouses -- Michigan
    - Fourteen Mile Point, Lake Superior (2 items), [1890] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 28)
    - [Hay Lake Channel Station], [1890] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 28)
    - Portage River (Jacobsville) (2 items), [1893] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 28)
  - American Lighthouses -- Minnesota
    - Duluth Range (2 items), [1893] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 29)
    - Two Harbors (4 items), [1893] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 29)
  - American Lighthouses -- New Hampshire
    - Dover -- submarine blasting, 1894 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 30)
    - Whaleback, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 30)
    - Island of Shoals (White Island) (4 items), undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 30)
  - American Lighthouses -- New Jersey
    - Barnegat -- General views (5 items), undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 31)
    - Barnegat -- Beach erosion series (by HBB) -- 4 boards each with 4 mounted photographs, 1919 Apr. 23 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 31)
    - Barnegat -- Beach erosion series (by HBB) -- 3 boards each with 3 mounted photographs, 1919 May 22 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 31)
    - Barnegat -- Beach erosion series (by HBB) -- 3 boards each with 3 mounted photographs, 1919 May 23 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 32)
    - Barnegat -- Beach erosion series (by HBB) -- 2 boards each with 4 mounted photographs, 1919 May 25 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 32)
    - Bergen Point (2 items), undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 33)
    - Conover Beacon, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 33)
    - Cross Ledge, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 33)
    - Hereford Inlet (2 items), 1913 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 33)
    - Navesink Twin Lights, 1885 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 33)
    - Newark Bay (3 items) (by Skinner), 1922 Jan. 20 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 33)
    - Passaic, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 34)
    - Point Comfort Range, 1884 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 34)
    - Sandy Hook -- General Views (one by Lamb) (2 items), 1884 1938 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 34)
    - Sandy Hook -- Fog Signals (2 items), 1884-1885 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 34)
    - Sandy Hook East Beacon, 1884 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 34)
  - American Lighthouses -- New York
    - Barber's Point, 1884 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 35)
    - Buffalo Breakwater, [1890] (Offsite-box 3, Folder 35)
    - Coxsackie, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 35)
    - Cumberland Head, 1886 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 35)
    - Danskammer Fog Bell, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 35)
    - Eatons Neck, [1885] (Offsite-box 3, Folder 35)
    - Elm Tree (2 items), 1899 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 35)
    - Esopus Meadows (2 items), [1884-1886] (Offsite-box 3, Folder 35)
    - Execution Rocks, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 35)
    - Fire Island, undated (Box Unknown container 565 for instance of Fire Island, Folder unknown container)
      General note
      See: Box 7, Folder 66
    - Fisher's Island Fog Bell (8 items), 1908 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 36)
    - Fort Columbus Fog Bell, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 37)
    - Fort Lafayette Fog Bell, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 37)
    - Fort Tompkins, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 37)